<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="vicinae_hotkey_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Aurelien Brabant

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="client-managed global hotkeys">
    This protocol lets a client choose, and freely reconfigure, its own
    global hotkeys: it requests a specific key combination and the compositor
    accepts it or rejects it with a reason. The compositor remains the eventual
    arbiter (it may deny a request, revoke a binding at any time, or apply
    whatever policy it likes), but within that the application manages its own
    bindings, including changing them at runtime, with no out-of-band user
    configuration and no persisted compositor state.

    A hotkey is a key combination that fires regardless of which surface holds
    keyboard focus. This is unrelated to keyboard-shortcuts-inhibit, which lets a
    focused client suppress the compositor's own shortcuts.

    Whether a combination is exclusive is compositor policy. A compositor MAY
    treat combinations as exclusive and reject a clashing request with
    "already_bound", or MAY grant the same combination to more than one binding
    (each bound hotkey then receives the events), as some platforms do. Clients
    must cope with either.

    It is intentionally a thin mechanism. It does NOT define which combinations
    are acceptable: that is policy and belongs to the compositor, expressed
    through the accept/deny channel. It does NOT persist hotkeys: a binding lives
    only as long as its vicinae_hotkey_v1 object and the client connection; there is
    no configure or storage step, a binding never outlives the client that created
    it, and reconfiguring is simply destroying a hotkey and binding the new
    combination.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward incompatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward compatible changes are added
    by bumping the interface version.

    Security considerations:

    A global hotkey lets an unfocused client observe that a specific key
    combination was pressed. Compositors are the security boundary and SHOULD
    apply policy when deciding whether to accept a request. In particular,
    implementations SHOULD reject combinations that do not include at least one
    non-latching modifier among Ctrl, Alt or Super, unless the trigger is a
    function key, because unmodified (and Shift-only) keys carry ordinary text
    entry and grabbing them turns this protocol into a keylogger.

    The protocol's one hard guarantee is containment: a compositor MUST NOT
    deliver events for a combination the client did not successfully bind, and
    never forwards the raw key stream, so a client learns nothing about input it
    did not explicitly, and successfully, bind. Beyond that, a compositor MAY
    apply any further policy it sees fit (for example prompting the user,
    restricting which clients may bind, or limiting how many bindings a client may
    hold) and MAY revoke a binding at any time via the "revoked" event, including
    under user control.

    These are recommendations, not wire requirements: a combination the
    compositor disallows is simply reported through the "denied" event with the
    "not_permitted" reason, so applications can rely on a uniform rejection path
    regardless of each compositor's policy.
  </description>

  <interface name="vicinae_hotkey_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="global hotkey factory">
      This interface is the entry point of the protocol. It is used to request
      global hotkeys.
    </description>

    <enum name="modifiers" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="modifier keys required by a hotkey">
        A bitmask of the modifiers that must be held for the hotkey to fire.

        These are fixed, keymap-independent semantic bits naming the standard
        modifiers, suitable for expressing a binding, unlike wl_keyboard.modifiers,
        which carries opaque, keymap-derived masks for runtime state. A compositor
        matches each bit against the corresponding modifier in its keyboard state
        as the keymap defines it; for the xkb_v1 keymap format that is shift ->
        XKB_MOD_NAME_SHIFT, ctrl -> XKB_MOD_NAME_CTRL, alt -> XKB_MOD_NAME_ALT
        ("Mod1"), super -> XKB_MOD_NAME_LOGO ("Mod4").

        Lock modifiers (Caps Lock, Num Lock) are never part of a binding and are
        ignored when matching.
      </description>
      <entry name="shift" value="1" summary="the Shift modifier"/>
      <entry name="ctrl" value="2" summary="the Control modifier"/>
      <entry name="alt" value="4" summary="the Alt modifier"/>
      <entry name="super" value="8" summary="the Super/Logo modifier"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager object. Hotkey objects created through this manager
        are unaffected and remain valid; their bindings persist until they are
        themselves destroyed or the client disconnects.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="bind">
      <description summary="request a global hotkey">
        Request that the given key combination be bound as a global hotkey.

        The keysym identifies the trigger key using the keysym numbering shared
        with the keymap delivered over wl_keyboard (for the xkb_v1 keymap format,
        an XKB_KEY_* value), taken in its unshifted form (XKB_KEY_b not XKB_KEY_B). A compositor SHOULD match
        it against any of the user's layout groups, so a binding keeps firing after
        the user switches layout group. This is one deliberately specified rule,
        not a universal one: other platforms differ (macOS matches a physical
        keycode, X11 re-grabs per layout, Windows tracks the active layout's key),
        and no rule serves a layout that never produces the keysym; the single
        documented rule is chosen for predictability across compositors.

        The request creates an vicinae_hotkey_v1 object immediately, but the binding
        is not active yet. The compositor replies asynchronously with either the
        "bound" event (the hotkey is now active) or the "denied" event (the
        request was rejected, with a reason).

        seat is the wl_seat whose keyboard should trigger the hotkey, or null to
        request it on all of the client's seats. Most clients pass null; seat is
        provided for completeness on multi-seat systems.

        app_id identifies the requesting application, for use in the compositor's
        policy and any user-facing audit UI. Where the application has a desktop
        entry, app_id SHOULD be its desktop file ID as defined by the
        freedesktop.org Desktop Entry specification, that is the .desktop file
        name with the .desktop suffix removed (for example "org.example.Launcher"),
        matching the convention used by xdg_toplevel.set_app_id so a compositor
        can correlate the two. It is advisory and may be spoofed; a compositor
        that needs a trustworthy identity SHOULD obtain it through the
        security-context mechanism rather than relying on this string.

        description is a human-readable, localized description of what the hotkey
		  does (e.g. "Toggle the launcher"), for display in compositor UI or even in this protocol error messages.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="vicinae_hotkey_v1"
           summary="the new hotkey object"/>
      <arg name="keysym" type="uint" summary="keysym of the trigger key (see description)"/>
      <arg name="modifiers" type="uint" enum="modifiers"
           summary="bitmask of required modifiers"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" allow-null="true"
           summary="target seat, or null for all of the client's seats"/>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string"
           summary="advisory application identifier (SHOULD be the desktop file ID)"/>
      <arg name="description" type="string"
           summary="human-readable action description"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="vicinae_hotkey_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a single global hotkey">
      Represents one requested global hotkey. Its binding is ephemeral: it is
      released when this object is destroyed or when the client disconnects, and
      it is never written to any persistent store.

      After bind, exactly one of "bound" or "denied" is sent. While the hotkey is
      bound, "pressed" and "released" are sent as the combination is activated.
      The compositor may send "revoked" at any time after "bound" to indicate the
      binding is no longer active (for example because the user removed it, or a
      higher-priority binding took the combination).
    </description>

    <enum name="deny_reason">
      <description summary="why a bind request was denied">
        Carried by the "denied" event. This is a reason code, not a fatal
        protocol error: the object remains valid and the client should destroy
        it (or try a different combination).
      </description>
      <entry name="already_bound" value="0"
             summary="already held by another hotkey the compositor treats as exclusive. The compositor is not obligated to give this level of detail and can just give not_permitted as the general 'deny' reason."/>
      <entry name="not_permitted" value="1"
             summary="the combination is disallowed by compositor policy"/>
      <entry name="invalid" value="2"
             summary="the keysym or combination is not a valid trigger"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="revoke_reason">
      <description summary="why a previously bound hotkey was withdrawn">
        Carried by the "revoked" event. This is a reason code, not a fatal
        protocol error: the object remains valid and the client should destroy
        it.

        The distinction is actionable: on "superseded" the combination may
        become available again, so a client may reasonably re-request it later;
        on "removed" the withdrawal is a deliberate user or compositor decision,
        so a client MUST NOT silently re-request the same combination. A client
        that receives a value it does not recognise (a future addition) MUST
        treat it conservatively as "removed" and not auto-rebind.
      </description>
      <entry name="removed" value="0"
             summary="withdrawn by the user or compositor; do not auto-rebind"/>
      <entry name="superseded" value="1"
             summary="a higher-priority binding took the combination; it may become available again"/>
      <entry name="not_permitted" value="2"
             summary="the combination is no longer allowed by compositor policy"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the hotkey">
        Release the binding and destroy the object. The combination becomes
        available again immediately. It is valid to destroy the object before
        receiving "bound" or "denied", which cancels the pending request.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="bound">
      <description summary="the hotkey is now active">
        The requested combination was accepted and is now active. "pressed" and
        "released" events may follow.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="denied">
      <description summary="the request was rejected">
        The requested combination was not bound. No input events will be sent.
        The client should destroy this object; it may then create a new request
        with a different combination.

        message is an optional, advisory, human-readable explanation in the
        compositor's locale, intended for verbatim display in client UI (for
        example a "change shortcut" settings screen). It may be empty, and a
        compositor is never required to provide it. Clients MUST NOT parse it or
        rely on its contents in any way; all programmatic behavior keys off
        reason. A client with nowhere to show it simply ignores it.
      </description>
      <arg name="reason" type="uint" enum="deny_reason" summary="why it was rejected"/>
      <arg name="message" type="string"
           summary="optional human-readable detail for display (may be empty)"/>
    </event>

    <event name="revoked">
      <description summary="a previously active hotkey was withdrawn">
        A binding that was previously "bound" is no longer active. No further
        input events will be sent for it. The client should destroy this object;
        it may request the combination again later.

        message is an optional, advisory, human-readable explanation in the
        compositor's locale, intended for verbatim display in client UI. It may
        be empty, and a compositor is never required to provide it. Clients MUST
        NOT parse it or rely on its contents in any way; all programmatic
        behavior keys off reason. A client with nowhere to show it simply
        ignores it.
      </description>
      <arg name="reason" type="uint" enum="revoke_reason" summary="why it was withdrawn"/>
      <arg name="message" type="string"
           summary="optional human-readable detail for display (may be empty)"/>
    </event>

    <event name="pressed">
      <description summary="the hotkey combination was pressed">
        The bound combination was activated.

        This event is sent once per activation. While the combination is held
        down no further "pressed" events are sent, and a single "released"
        follows when the trigger key is released: the compositor does not
        auto-repeat the hotkey.

        serial is a compositor-issued input serial that counts as a recent user
        interaction, so the client can act on the hotkey even though the
        triggering key press is not otherwise delivered to it (the compositor
        consumes it). In particular, a client may pass this serial to
        xdg_activation_token_v1.set_serial in order to raise or focus a surface in
        response to the hotkey; a compositor SHOULD honor activation carried by
        this serial, since the hotkey is itself a deliberate user action. The
        serial is drawn from the same space as other input event serials.

        time is the event timestamp, with the same millisecond clock as wl_pointer
        and wl_keyboard input events; it is useful for ordering and for measuring
        press-to-release duration.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="input serial for the activation (e.g. xdg-activation)"/>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="timestamp in milliseconds"/>
    </event>

    <event name="released">
      <description summary="the hotkey combination was released">
        The trigger key of a previously pressed combination was released. This
        enables press-and-hold uses (e.g. push-to-talk); clients that only act
        on activation may ignore it.

        serial and time have the same meaning as in the "pressed" event.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="input serial for the activation (e.g. xdg-activation)"/>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="timestamp in milliseconds"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
